A Finding Aid to the Betty Parsons Gallery records and personal papers, circa 1920-1991, bulk 1946-1983, in the Archives of American Art AAA.parsbett
Archives of American Art
- Betty Parsons Personal Papers, circa 1927-1991; Series 7; (Boxes 38-51; 11.5 linear feet)
  - Writings by Others, circa 1950-1980; 7.6
    Found here are articles, poems, essays, and unpublished manuscripts mostly about Parsons and the Betty Parsons Gallery, including a typescript for an unpublished monograph, "An American Gallery," written by art critic Lawrence Alloway. Related correspondence can be found in the Alloway folders in the Betty Parsons Papers Correspondence files. Also included is a proposal for a documentary film about Betty Parsons titled "Keeper of the Treasure"; it does not appear that this project was realized. Other writings are related to art, dance, and poetry, including a notebook of poems by Parsons Gallery artist, Dorothy Sturm.
    Files are arranged by alphabetically by author, followed by one file of miscellaneous essays and poems.
    - Alloway, Lawrence, typescript of "An American Gallery,", circa 1961-1968; (3 folders) (Box 42, Folder 24-26)
    - Codman, Florence, typescript of "Values in Some Recent American Paintings,", undated (Box 42, Folder 27)
    - Dlugoszewski, Lucia, miscellaneous writings, circa 1962-1972 (Box 42, Folder 28)
    - Dreyfuss, Caril, typescript of "On Judging,", 1980 (Box 42, Folder 29)
    - Du Brul, E. Lloyd, "Biology of Artistic Behavior,", 1968 (Box 42, Folder 30)
    - Hawkins, Erick, miscellaneous writings, circa 1961-1962 (Box 42, Folder 31)
    - [Martin, Agnes], manuscript (photocopy) of "Current of the River of Life Moves Us,", undated (Box 42, Folder 32)
    - Mathieu, Georges, typescript of "Declaration to the American Avant Garde Painters,", undated (Box 42, Folder 33)
    - McFadden, Elizabeth, typescript of "Anthology for Children,", undated (Box 42, Folder 34)
    - McFadden, Elizabeth, typescript of "Poetry Edition,", undated (Box 42, Folder 35)
    - Motherwell, Robert, typescript of "In Memoriam: Anthony Smith,", 1981 (Box 42, Folder 36)
    - Putnam, Wallace, photocopy of talk "Come Dance with Dragon,", 1971 (Box 42, Folder 37)
    - Putnam, Wallace, typescript of "The Shiny Gilt Frame is Gone,", undated (Box 42, Folder 38)
    - Sturm, Dorothy, notebook of poems, 1957 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - unknown author, proposal for "Keeper of the Treasure,", circa 1981 (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous typescripts, circa 1950-1965 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Printed Materials, circa 1920-1991; 7.7
    Printed Material includes catalogs and announcements for exhibitions at Betty Parsons Gallery and other galleries, offsets of articles, magazines, clippings from newspapers and magazines.
    Announcements and catalogs files include printed material from the Wakefield Gallery, Mortimer Brandt Gallery, Betty Parsons Gallery, as well as other galleries. Much of this material is duplicated in other series including Artists Files and Other Gallery Records.
    The bulk of magazine and newspaper clippings feature Betty Parsons in her role as artist, art dealer, or collector. The file of the 1967 House and Garden feature on her Long Island Studio includes photographs, some of which appear to have been used in the article. This subseries also includes clippings on artists, particularly those whom Parsons represented, general art and architecture files, and a file of miscellaneous clippings and cartoons.
    Much of this subseries has not been scanned. Digitized materials include announcements and catalogs (only the cover and title page have been scanned for some printed catalogs), clippings about Parsons, and clippings about her friends and family.
    - Announcements and Catalogs, 1927-1952 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Announcements and Catalogs, 1952-1966 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Announcements and Catalogs, 1967-1982 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Magazine Clippings about Betty Parsons, circa 1951-1982; (2 folders) (Box 43, Folder 7-8)
    - Magazine Clippings and photographs of Betty Parsons' Studio, circa 1967 (Box 43, Folder 9)
    - Magazine Clippings about Art and Architecture, circa 1951-1982; (2 folders, not scanned) (Box 43, Folder 10-11)
    - Magazine Clippings about Artists, circa 1947-1948; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 43, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper Clippings about Betty Parsons, circa 1930-1983; (2 folders) (Box 43, Folder 13-14)
    - Newspaper Clippings about Friends and Family, circa 1920-1960 (Box 43, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper Clippings about Art and Architecture, circa 1948-1978; (2 folders, not scanned) (Box 43, Folder 16-17)
    - Newspaper Clippings about Artists, circa 1927-1976; (2 folders, not scanned) (Box 43, Folder 18-19)
    - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, Miscellaneous, circa 1945-1971; (Not scanned) (Box 43, Folder 20)
    - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, Duplicates, circa 1957-1982; (3 folders, not scanned) (Box 43, Folder 21-23)
    - Magazines, 1946-1983; (4 folders, not scanned) (Box 43, Folder 24-27)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950-1991; (Not scanned) (Box 43, Folder 28)
  - Records About Betty Parsons' Art Work, circa 1927-1983; 7.8
    These files chronicle Betty Parsons' artistic career through announcements, catalogs, correspondence, inventories, price lists, sales invoices, loan forms and photographs. The majority of photographs are reproductions of works of art, although installation shots are scattered throughout.
    The bulk of this subseries has been scanned, except for photographs, transparencies, and slides of artwork.
    - Annoucements and Catalogs, circa 1927-1982 (Box 43, Folder 29)
    - Exhibition files (Box 43)
      - General Exhibitions, circa 1927-1956 (Box 43, Folder 30)
      - General Exhibitions, circa 1957-1969 (Box 43, Folder 31)
      - General Exhibitions, 1970-1979 (Box 43, Folder 32)
      - New Arts Gallery (1963: Atlanta, Ga.), 1962-1965 (Box 43, Folder 33)
      - Miami Museum of Modern Art (1963), circa 1962-1963 (Box 43, Folder 34)
      - New Gallery (1966: Bennington College, Vt.), 1965-1966 (Box 43, Folder 35)
      - Gallery Seven (1967: Boston, Mass.) (Box 43, Folder 36)
      - Grand Central Moderns (1967: New York, N.Y.), 1966-1967 (Box 43, Folder 37)
      - Whitechapel Gallery (1968: London, England), 1965-1969; (4 folders) (Box 44, Folder 1-4)
      - Studio Gallery (1971: Washington, D.C.), 1971-1972; (2 folders) (Box 44, Folder 5-6)
      - College Art Gallery (1972: Drew University, Madison, N.J.), 1971-1972 (Box 44, Folder 7)
      - A.M. Sachs Gallery (1972: New York, N.Y.) (Box 44, Folder 8)
      - Studio Gallery (1973: Washington, D.C.), 1972-1975 (Box 44, Folder 9)
      - Montclair Art Museum (1974: Montclair, N.J.), circa 1974; (3 folders) (Box 44, Folder 10-12)
      - Studio Gallery (1975: Washington, D.C.), (2 folders) (Box 44, Folder 13)
      - Benson Gallery (1975: Bridgehampton, N.Y.), 1974-1975 (Box 44, Folder 14)
      - Circanou Galleries (1976: Des Moines, Iowa), 1975 (Box 44, Folder 15)
        Exhibition was cancelled.
      - David Hendricks Gallery (1976: Dublin,Ireland) (Box 44, Folder 16)
      - Louise Himelfarb Gallery (1977: Water Mill,N.Y.) (Box 44, Folder 17)
      - Barnard College (1977: New York, N.Y.) (Box 44, Folder 18)
      - United States Information Service (1978: Tegucilgalpa, Hondoras) (Box 44, Folder 19)
      - Heath Gallery (1978: Atlanta,Ga.), 1977-1979 (Box 44, Folder 20)
      - Artists and Poets fo the Hamptons Landscape,Benson Gallery (1978: Bridgehamton, N.Y.) (Box 44, Folder 21)
      - Kornblee/Truman Gallery (1978: New York, N.Y.), 1978-1979 (Box 44, Folder 22)
      - Paintings and Sculptures by Candidates for Art Awards, American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters (1979: New York, N.Y.), 1977-1979 (Box 44, Folder 23)
      - Women Artists of Eastern New York, Guild Hall (1979: East Hampton, N.Y.) (Box 44, Folder 24)
      - Hoshour Gallery (1979: Albuquerque, New Mexico), 1978-1979 (Box 44, Folder 25)
      - Marchand-Parson Gallery (1979: Shelter Island, N.Y.), circa 1979 (Box 44, Folder 26)
      - Summit Art Center (1979: Summit, N.J.) (Box 44, Folder 27)
      - Zeller Gallery (1979: University Park, Penn.) (Box 44, Folder 28)
      - Fairweather Hardin Gallery (1979: Chicago, Ill.) (Box 44, Folder 29)
      - Kornblee Galleries (1980: New York, N.Y.), 1980-1983 (Box 44, Folder 30)
      - Barbara Fiedler Gallery (1980: Washington D.C.), 1979-1982 (Box 44, Folder 31)
      - Newspace (1980: Los Angeles, Calif.), 1979-1982 (Box 44, Folder 32)
      - American Center (1980: Paris, France), 1979-1980 (Box 44, Folder 33)
      - Nigel Greenwood Inc. Ltd. (1980: London, England), 1980-1981 (Box 44, Folder 34)
      - Robert T. Kidd Associates (1980: Birmingham, Mich.), 1980-1983 (Box 44, Folder 35)
      - Portraits Real and Imagined, Guild Hall (1980: East Hampton, N.Y.) (Box 44, Folder 36)
      - William Sawyer Gallery (1981: San Franisco, Calif.) (Box 44, Folder 37)
      - Virginia Miller Galleries (1981: Miami, Fla.), 1980-1981 (Box 44, Folder 38)
      - Burnside Gallery (1981: Greenport, N.Y.) (Box 44, Folder 39)
      - Benson Gallery (1981: Bridgehampton, N.Y.), 1980-1981 (Box 44, Folder 40)
      - The Artist and the Quilt, Traveling Exhibition (1980), 1980-1982; (2 folders) (Box 44, Folder 41-42)
      - Hoshour Gallery (1982: Albuquerque, New Mexico), 1981-1982 (Box 44, Folder 43)
      - Betty Parsons Memorial Show, Betty Parsons Gallery (1982: New York, N.Y.) (Box 44, Folder 44)
      - Fairweather Hardin (1982: Chicago, Ill.), 1982-1983 (Box 44, Folder 45)
    - Inventories, 1966-1982 (Box 44, Folder 46)
    - Inventory with Sketches, 1982 October (Box 44, Folder 47)
    - Inventories, 1983 (Box 44, Folder 48)
    - Appraisals and Price Lists, 1979-1983 (Box 44, Folder 49)
    - Consignments, 1941-1967 (Box 44, Folder 50)
    - Consignments, 1974-1979 (Box 44, Folder 51)
    - Consignments, circa 1980-1983 (Box 44, Folder 52)
    - Consignments-Heath Gallery, Atlanta, Georgia, 1980-1982 (Box 44, Folder 53)
    - Sales, 1938-1982 (Box 44, Folder 54)
    - Photographs of Betty Parsons Sculptures at the National Gallery of Art Opening, 1973 November (Box 44, Folder 55)
    - Installation Photographs, New Arts Gallery, Atlanta, Georgia, circa 1962-1964 (Box 44, Folder 56)
    - Miscellaneous Installation Photographs, circa 1962-1980 (Box 44, Folder 57)
    - Photographs of Paintings, circa 1940-1980; (5 folders; not scanned) (Box 44, Folder 58-62)
    - Photographs of Wood Sculptures, circa 1970s; (Not scanned) (Box 44, Folder 63)
    - Photographs of Paintings and Sculptures, 1980-1982; (Not scanned) (Box 44, Folder 64)
    - Photographs, Duplicates, circa 1940-1980; (Not scanned) (Box 44, Folder 65)
    - Color Separations for Art Gallery Magazine, 1972 October; (Not scanned) (Box 44, Folder 66)
    - Negatives for Color Separation for Annoucement, 1973; (Not scanned) (Box 44, Folder 67)
    - Transparencies, circa 1970-1981; (Not scanned) (Box 44, Folder 68)
    - Slides, circa 1970s; (Not Scanned) (Box 44, Folder 69)
  - Betty Parsons Private Collection, circa 1963-1983; 7.9
    This subseries documents Betty Parsons' personal art collection through inventories, correspondence, clippings, photographs, loan agreements, sales and purchase invoices, and photographs of artwork.
    Institutions and museums often requested loans from Parsons' personal collection for exhibitions. Exhibition files consist of announcements, catalogs, correspondence, and clippings. Additionally Parsons' gave works of art from her collection to institutions and museums and these gifts are recorded in the "Gifts of work" files. Some of the documents in this subseries document appraisals of the collection following Parsons' death in 1982
    The bulk of this subseries has been scanned except for photographs of works of art.
    - Appraisals, 1983 (Box 44, Folder 70)
    - Correspondence, circa 1968-1981 (Box 44, Folder 71)
    - Inventories, circa 1971-1983 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Exhibitions (Box 45)
      - Finch College (1968: New York, N.Y.) (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - New York Painting and Sculpture: 1940-1970, Metropolitan Museum of Art(1969: New York, N.Y.), 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 3)
      - Montclair Museum of Art(1972: Montclair, N.J.), 1971-1972 (Box 45, Folder 4)
      - Parrish Art Museum (1972: Southampton, N.Y.) (Box 45, Folder 5)
      - Art of this Century from the Betty Parsons Collection, Rhode Island School of Design (1980: Providence, R.I.), 1979-1980 (Box 45, Folder 6)
    - General Exhibition Annoucements and Catalogues, circa 1963-1983 (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - General Exhibition Loan Forms and Correspondence, 1966-1982 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Gifts of Works of Art, 1956-1970 (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Gifts of Works of Art, 1971-1977 (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - Gifts of Works of Art, 1978 (Box 45, Folder 11)
    - Gifts of Works of Art, 1979-1980 (Box 45, Folder 12)
    - Gifts of Works of Art, 1980-1981 (Box 45, Folder 13)
    - Gifts of Works of Art, 1982 (Box 45, Folder 14)
    - Sales and Purchases, 1961-1977 (Box 45, Folder 15)
    - Photographs, circa 1955-1982; (4 folders; not scanned) (Box 45, Folder 16-19)
    - Photographs, Duplicates, circa 1955-1982; (4 folders; not scanned) (Box 45, Folder 20-23)
    - Transparencies and Negatives, circa 1967-1983; (Not scanned) (Box 45, Folder 24)
  - Personal Financial Records, 1947-1980; 7.10; (Not scanned)
    Records in this extensive subseries provide insights into Parsons' personal financial affair documenting her investments, banking accounts, family estates (including her own will and testament) and real estate holdings. Since her work as an art dealer was her primary source of income, financial information relevant to the Betty Parsons Gallery can be found within her personal tax records.
    The personal financial records have arranged into five subseries:
    7.10.1: Family Financial Papers, 1948-1979
    7.10.2: Real Estate Files,
    7.10.3: Investments and Securities,
    7.10.4: Tax Records,
    7.10.5: Banking Records,
    This subseries has not been scanned.
    - Family Financial Papers, 1948-1979; 7.10.1
      - Betty Parsons' Last Will and Testament, 1975-1979 (Box 45, Folder 25)
      - Estate of J. Fred Pierson, 1955-1961 (Box 45, Folder 26)
      - Estate of James R. Pierson, 1975-1979 (Box 45, Folder 27)
      - Miscellaneous Pierson Family Estate Papers, 1948-1959 (Box 45, Folder 28)
      - Estate of Emily P. Rayner, 1963-1977; (2 folders) (Box 45, Folder 29-30)
    - Real Estate Records, circa 1951-1982; 7.10.2
      - Miscellaneous Real Estate Documents, 1958-1975 (Box 45, Folder 31)
      - Artists Acres, Englewood, Fla., circa 1951-1966 (Box 45, Folder 32)
      - House in Sheepscott, Maine, circa 1973-1981; (4 Folders) (Box 45, Folder 33-36)
      - House in St. Maartens, Netherlands Antilles, circa 1968-1982; (9 Folders) (Box 45, Folder 37-45)
      - St. Maartens, Netherlands Antilles, House Plans, circa 1962-1966; (3 Folders) (Box 45, Folder 46-48)
      - St. Maartens, Netherlands Antilles, Landowners Association, circa 1961-1981; (4 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 1-4)
    - Investments and Securities, circa 1948-1981; 7.10.3
      - Automobile Insurance Policies, circa 1963-1978; (2 folders) (Box 46, Folder 5-6)
      - Miscellaneous Employees Insurance Policies, circa 1960-1974 (Box 46, Folder 7)
      - Fine Arts Dealers Insurance Policies, 1972-1978 (Box 46, Folder 8)
      - Personal Fine Arts Insurance Policies, 1971-1976 (Box 46, Folder 9)
      - Health and Medicare Insurance Policies, 1962-1966 (Box 46, Folder 10)
      - Homeowners Insurance Policies, 1961-1978 (Box 46, Folder 11)
      - Miscellaneous Insurance Policies, 1963-1974 (Box 46, Folder 12)
      - Miles Timber Company, 1948-1977; (2 folders) (Box 46, Folder 13-14)
      - Miles Timber Company Audit Reports, 1951-1962; (2 folders) (Box 46, Folder 15-16)
      - Ramapo Land Company, 1958-1982 (Box 46, Folder 17)
      - Ramapo Land Company Financial Statements, 1966-1969 (Box 46, Folder 18)
      - Chemical Bank Investment Statements, 1969-1970 (Box 46, Folder 19)
      - Chemical Bank Investment Statements, 1971-1972 (Box 46, Folder 20)
      - Chemical Bank Investment Statements, 1972-1973 (Box 46, Folder 21)
      - Chemical Bank Investment Statements, 1977-1978 (Box 46, Folder 22)
      - Chemical Bank Investment Statements, 1978-1979 (Box 46, Folder 23)
      - Chemical Bank Investment Statements, 1979 (Box 46, Folder 24)
      - Irving Trust Company, 1959-1967 (Box 46, Folder 25)
      - Investment Accounts, 1959-1979; (13 folders) (Box 46, Folder 26-38)
      - Securities Statements, 1969-1975; (3 folders) (Box 46, Folder 39-41)
    - Tax Records, circa 1940-1979; 7.10.4
      - Tax Documents (1940-1943), 1941-1944 (Box 46, Folder 42)
      - Tax Documents (1954-1957), 1955-1958 (Box 46, Folder 43)
      - Tax Documents (1958-1959), 1959-1960 (Box 46, Folder 44)
      - Tax Documents (1960-1964), 1960-1965 (Box 46, Folder 45)
      - Tax Documents (1965-1966), 1965-1967 (Box 46, Folder 46)
      - Tax Documents (1967), 1967-1968 (Box 46, Folder 47)
      - Tax Documents (1968), 1968-1970 (Box 46, Folder 48)
      - Tax Documents (1969), 1968-1973 (Box 47, Folder 1)
      - Tax Documents (1970), 1968-1971 (Box 47, Folder 2)
      - Tax Documents (1971), 1971-1973 (Box 47, Folder 3)
      - Tax Documents (1972), 1972-1973 (Box 47, Folder 4)
      - Tax Documents (1973), 1973-1974 (Box 47, Folder 5)
      - Tax Documents (1974), 1974-1975 (Box 47, Folder 6)
      - Tax Documents (1975-1977), 1975-1978 (Box 47, Folder 7)
      - Tax Documents (1979), 1979-1980 (Box 47, Folder 8)
      - Property Taxes, Town of Southold, 1959-1974 (Box 47, Folder 9)
      - Property Taxes, Town of Esopus, 1968-1973 (Box 47, Folder 10)
      - Real Estate Taxes, Sarasota County, 1963-1973 (Box 47, Folder 11)
      - Social Security, 1965-1974 (Box 47, Folder 12)
      - Financial Contributions, circa 1960-1978 (Box 47, Folder 13)
      - Miscellaneous Receipts, circa 1958-1979; (23 folders) (Box 47, Folder 14-36)
      - Miscellaneous Receipts, circa 1958-1979; (4 folders) (Box 48, Folder 1-4)
    - Banking Records, 1953-1982; 7.10.5
      - Bank Correspondence, 1961-1982 (Box 48, Folder 5)
      - Citibank (formerly First National City Bank), 1966-1979; (17 Folders) (Box 48, Folder 6-22)
      - Citibank (formerly First National City Bank), 1966-1979; (13 Folders) (Box 49, Folder 1-13)
      - Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company, 1953-1980; (13 Folders) (Box 49, Folder 14-26)
      - North Fork Bank and Trust, 1963-1979; (4 Folders) (Box 49, Folder 27-30)
      - North Fork Bank and Trust, 1963-1979; (10 Folders) (Box 50, Folder 1-10)
      - Windward Islands Bank, circa 1973-1982; (4 Folders) (Box 50, Folder 11-14)